Guide to the Sean Prendiville Papers AIA.005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sean Prendiville Papers
1818-1997
1920-1997
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Prendiville, Sean
AIA.005
4.75 Linear Feet in 2 manuscript boxes, 3 record cartons, and 1 oversized flat box.
Sean Prendiville is a first-generation Irish American, born and raised in San Francisco, California. Members of the Prendiville family living in Ireland were active Republicans during the Irish War of Independence (1919-1921) and the Irish Civil War (1922-1923). Prendiville joined Irish support groups established in San Francisco during confict in Northern Ireland in the late 1960s. This collection contains material concerning the Irish American experience with specific focus on Northern California. Materials include personal correspondence and other documentation regarding numerous Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests made by Prendiville to the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) concerning several Irish American individuals and organizations suspected of Irish Republican activity from approximately 1920 to 1979. Also included are original letters written by a Fenian prisoner in Western Australia in 1870, as well as newspaper accounts from the same time period. The collection also includes ephemera and physical objects, including flyers, newspapers, broadsides, bumper stickers, and a singificant button collection supprting Irish prisoners and the Republican movement.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into five series. Series are arranged alphabetically, then chronologically.
Missing Title
Series I. Correspondence, 1902-1997
Series II. Subject Files, 1864-1988
Series III. Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Requests and Correspondence, 1920-1979
Series IV. Printed Ephemera, 1818-1924
Series V. Nonprint, 1980-1995
Biographical Note
Sean Prendiville is a first generation Irish American, born and raised in San Francisco, California. His father emigrated from County Kerry, his mother from County Roscommon. In Ireland, members of the Prendiville family were active Republicans during the country's fight for independence from Great Britain (1919-1921) and subsequent civil war (1922-1923). Two of Sean Prendiville's grand-uncles were in the Irish Republican Army (IRA): one was killed in a raid on a Royal Irish Constabulary (police) station in Castleisland, County Kerry; the other continued to fight with the IRA until he was wounded and captured during the civil war. Their nephew in San Francisco regularly took young Sean Prendiville to buy the Sinn Fein newspaper The United Irishman at the Golden Gate News Agency on Third Street.
When conflict broke out in Northern Ireland in 1968, following attacks on Northern Ireland Civil Rights Association marches, Sean Prendiville joined some of the Irish support groups that were established in San Francisco. Later, after the Republican movement split, he joined the Irish Republican Clubs, supporters of the Official Irish Republican movement, because their politics seemed more in line with the anti-Vietnam war movement that he was also participating in at the time. While a member of the Irish Republican Clubs, Prendiville met some older activists who had participated in the Irish Republican Congress Clubs of the 1930s, especially Vernon Healey in San Francisco and Gerald O'Reilly in New York. He became aware of a current in Irish-American and Irish Republican history that had been passed over - the links between left-wing Irish organizations and American progressives – sparking a research interest that eventually led to the assembly of this collection between 1986 and 1994
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Related Materials
George Harrison Papers AIA 009
Irish Republicanism Collection AIA 022
Patrick Daugton Collection AIA 055
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents Sean Prendiville's involvement in and research on the activities of Irish and Irish American organizations in the 20th century, with a specific focus on Irish Republicanism. Materials include flyers, pamphlets, broadsides, buttons, bumper stickers, correspondence, newspapers, government forms, Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests, and Federal Bureau of Investigation documents. The majority of the collection consists of Prendiville's FOIA requests and the documents he received in response. These materials focused on Irish organizations in Ireland and the United States under surveillance for alleged Irish Republican activities.
Separated Materials
The 19th century publication The Phoenix was separated from this collection and integrated into the Archives of Irish America Newspapers and Periodicals Collection (AIA 004) as Box 185.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Sean Prendiville donated the documents to the Archives of Irish America at the Tamiment Library, NYU in June 1997, July 1998, August 1998, August 2004, and 2011. The series of personal correspondence came to the Archives along with the Patrick Daughton Papers (AIA 055) in 2009. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1997.059 and 2011.005.
An additional accretion was donated in 2018. The accession number associated with this gift is 2018.102.
Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; New York (N.Y.).; Irish Americans -- New York (State) -- New York -- Political activity.; Philadelphia (Pa.); Correspondence.; San Francisco (Calif.); Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Freedom of information -- Government policy -- United States.; Reports.; Clippings (information artifacts); Bumper stickers.; Buttons (information artifacts).; Prisoners' writings, Irish.; Articles.; McAliskey, Bernadette Devlin, 1947-; O'Reilly, Gerald, 1903-1990; United States. Federal Bureau of Investigation; United Irish Republicans; National Association for Irish Justice; Irish Republican Clubs; Irish Republican Brotherhood Veterans Association; James Connolly Clubs; National Association for Irish Freedom (U.S.); Clan-na-Gael; Irish American Labor League; Irish Republican Army; Women's Irish Educational League; Gralton, Jimmy, 1886-1945
- Series I. Correspondence, 1902-1997
  Scope and Content Note
  This series consists of personal correspondence between Prendiville and numerous individuals. Of note are two folders of letters between Prendiville and Gerald O'Reily, a prominent member of the New York City Transit Workers Union (TWU) and a contemporary of TWU President Mike Quill. Materials in the correspondence concern Irish Republicans Frank Ryan and Father Michael O' Flanagan.
  - Conway, Neil J., 1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Cork Workers Club, 1978; cuid14939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curtis, Liz (author), 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General; mostly Celtic Network I, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - General; mostly Celtic Network II, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 3A)
  - Irish American Voice (Entertprise, AL), 1985; cuid14940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - O'Reilly, Gerald (Local 100, TWU, NYC) I, 1902-1990; cuid14941 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - O'Reilly, Gerald (Local 100, TWU, NYC) II, 1902-1990; cuid14942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Queen's University of Belfast Conference Invitation, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Research and Correspondence (includes two unidentified photographs), 1985-1997; cuid14943 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Irish American Unity Conference: Membership papers, 1984; cuid14944 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1864-1988
  This series consists of original letters, newspaper clippings, periodicals, and form letters collected by Prendiville on Irish republican politics and the escape and rescue of Fenian prisoners held in Western Australia by the American whaling ship the Catalpa in the late 19th century. The series includes publications produced by The Workers Party (Ireland), including a manifesto, newsletters, pamphlets, and issues of the Student Workers Party Bulletin. Periodical titles include The Irish Felon, The Felon, The Harp, Voice of Freedom, and Irish Republican Newsletter. The form letters were sent by the National Association for Irish Justice and the National Association for Irish Freedom.
  - Catalpa: article in The Western Austrlian Times, Apr 21, 1876; cuid15097 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Catalpa: correspondence, newspaper accounts (very rare) Note: Most of the Catalpa-related material appears to be correspondence written to or from John B. Walsh, a Fenian who was transported to Australia after the Fenian Rising was broken up. Walsh was released after one of the round of amnesties, either 1869 or 1871, and settled in San Francisco. Transcriptions are included for some of the letters., 1864-1895 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Irish republican periodicals and documents, 1909-1984 (Box Shared Tamiment 030, Folder 1-5, Box Shared Tamiment 031, Folder 1)
  - Irish Republican Prisoners and Dependents Fund: Biographies of speakers and others, circa 1920; cuid15098 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - The Workers Party (Belfast): Manifesto, Newsletters, Pamphlets, Students Workers Party Bulletin, 1987-1988; cuid15099 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Series III: Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Requests and Correspondence, 1920-1992
  This series consists of administrative papers, government forms, and other documents related to Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) requests and appeals made by Prendiville from 1986 to 1994. The files contains photocopies of memoranda, letters, and reports generated by the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) in the course of their surveillance of Irish Republican activities in the United States between 1930 and 1979. Also included are newspaper and magazine articles, brochures, and other literature distributed by Irish American organizations under investigation. Many files contain collections of clippings from Irish publications, especially newspapers produced by support groups, that no longer exist and for which there may be no surviving copies. Organizations present in this series include the Irish Republican Clubs, Clan na Gael, James Connolly Clubs, the Irish American Labor League, the Irish Republican Army (IRA), Irish Republican Clubs (IRC), National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF), the National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ), and The Citizens for Irish Justice (CIJ). Specific individuals such as James Gralton and James Larkin also appear. Much of the material is heavily redacted.
  Arrangement
  Files in this series are arranged according to the FBI's original identification and sequence numbers. The FBI assigned each organization a sequence number. For example, the Irish Republican Clubs are identified by the number 97-5329. Each specific document relating to that organization was then numbered sequentially; for example, 97-5329-25 identifies the twenty-fifth document in approximately chronological order. The FBI files also contain records that were filed under more than one organization; when cross-referenced like this, the documents do not have a sequence number. The order in which documents were supplied by the FBI has been maintained except when unknown; then they are filed chronologically.
  - Correspondence re: FOIA requests, 1986-1994; cuid14945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Government Materials - non-FBI, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Clan na Gael c. 97-4883-1-97-4883-17, Mar 1964-Oct 1964; cuid14946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clan na Gael c. 97-4883-18-97-4883-40, Oct 1964-Sep 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Gralton, James 65-35485-1;65-35485-5, Jun 1943-Oct 1944; cuid14947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Irish American Labor League c. 61-179-1-61-179-32, Oct 1921-Feb 1922 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Irish American Labor League: Case 75, 75A, Doc. C. 127-152pages c. 14160-14213 (reports of agents, summary memos), Apr 1921-May 1921; cuid14948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Irish American Labor League: Case 75, 75A, Doc. C. 153-201pages c. 14215 - 14295, May 1921-Jun 1921; cuid14949 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Irish American Labor League: Reports, memos related to Case 75pages c. 14298-14333 (illegible), Mar 1921, 1922; cuid14950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Irish Radio Shows, 1970; cuid14951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-1-61-7606-50, Sep 1939-Jul 1940; cuid14952 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-51-61-7606-83, Jul 1940-Feb 1942 (bulk 1920-1997); cuid14953 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-84-61-7606-144, Jan 1942-Jan 1943; cuid14954 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-145-61-7606-209, Feb 1943-May 1943; cuid14955 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-210-61-7606-260 I, May 1943-Oct 1943; cuid14956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-145-61-7606-260 II, May 1943-Oct 1943; cuid14957 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-261-61-7606-342 I, Sep 1943-Dec 1944; cuid14958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-261-61-7606-342 II, Sep 1943-Dec 1943; cuid14959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-343-61-7606-393, Feb 1945-May 1950; cuid14960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-394-61-7606-451, Sep 1951-Oct 1957; cuid14961 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-452-61-7606-501, Oct 1957-Nov 1963; cuid14962 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-502-61-7606- c. 520s(some documents not numbered, cross-referenced), Nov 1963-Nov 1969; cuid14963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-?-61-7606-575(Some documents not completely numbered), Dec 1969-Oct 1972; cuid14964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-576-61-7606-653, Oct 1972-Feb 1974; cuid14965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-654-61-7606-721, Feb 1974-Feb 1975; cuid14966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-722-61-7606-831 I, Feb 1975-May 1977; cuid14967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-722-61-7606-831 II, Feb 1975-May 1979; cuid14968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Irish Republican Army c. 61-7606-A: news clippings, wire services - U.S, Ireland, U.K. events, 1939-1975; cuid14969 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Irish Republican Brotherhood Veterans Association (FOIA #270, 640), 1992; cuid14970 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-1-97-5329-16, Mar 1971-Sep 1971; cuid14971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-17-97-5329-31, Sep 1971-Jun 1972; cuid14972 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-32-97-5329-52, Feb 1972-Nov 1972; cuid14973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-53-97-5329-81 I, Nov 1972-Jun 1975; cuid14974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-53-97-5329-81 II, Nov 1972-Jun 1975; cuid14975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Irish Republican Clubs c. 97-5329-82-97-5329-112, Jul 1975-Aug 1979; cuid14976 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Irish Workers Clubs, 1940-1955; cuid14977 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - James Connolly Clubs 62-17493-0, 1920-1924, 1943; cuid14978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - James Gralton Defense Committee 9 FOIA #270, 234), 1986; cuid14979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - James Larkin Defense Committee ( FOIA #270, 233), 1986; cuid14980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-1 (Numbers not visible), Apr 1971; cuid14981 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-2-1053212344-19 I, Jun 1971-Nov 1971; cuid14982 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-2-1053212344-19 II, Jun 1971-Nov 1971; cuid14983 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-21-105-212344-46 ( 20, 28 missing) I, Nov 1971-Jan 1973; cuid14984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-21-105-212344-46 ( 20, 28 missing) II, Nov 1971-Jan 1973; cuid14985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - National Association for Irish Freedom (NAIF) c. 105-212344-47-105-212344-64 ( missing # 52 encl.), Jan 1973-Apr 1979; cuid14986 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275 -xl- 97-5275-9, Aug 1969-Dec 1969; cuid14987 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-10-97-5275-25, Dec 1969-Mar 1970; cuid14988 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-28-97-5275-35, Mar 1970-Jun 1970; cuid14989 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-36-97-5275-59 I, Jul 1970-Nov 1970; cuid14990 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-36-97-5275-59 II, Jul 197-Nov 1970; cuid14991 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - National Association for Irish Justice (NAIJ) c. 97-5275-60-97-5275-88, Nov 1970-Apr 1972; cuid14992 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - United Irish Republicans (FOIA #297, 643), 1992; cuid14993 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Women's Irish Educational League (FOAI #297, 646; Appeal #89-1-11), 1989; cuid14994 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reference: Index to organization of material (SP), 1986-1994; cuid14995 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series IV. Printed Ephemera, 1818-1924
  This series consists of flyers, pamphlets, broadsides, and other materials demonstrating support for various 20th century Irish Republican and Irish American support groups.
  - Bond Certificates - Republic of Ireland - flier and postcard, 1918-1919 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Book - Love Orange Love Green Whitcor Publications Inscribed, circa 1973 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Cunningham, Michael, Monaghan County of Intrigue, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Eddie Rabbit, 1975-1986 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Fliers and Broadsides: includes: "The truth about the Clan na Gael;" "The Irish World's Indictment of James G. Blaine;" "Brother Jonathan to the A.P.A.", 1818-1920, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Notes for an article by Gerry Foley, undated (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Pamphlet - "Christmas in Northern Ireland..." National Assoc. for Irish Freedom, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Pamphlet - Class Against Class Marxist-Leninist Org. of Britain, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Pamphlet - Lemane, Cornelius "The Irish Republic", 1916 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Pamphlet - Lysaght, O'Connor, The Limerick Soviet, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Pamphlet - O'Connell, Emmett, Dail Vladh: Shaping A New Society, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Pamphlet - Workers Solidarity Movement, Ireland and British Imperialism, 1992 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Publication: Brennan's: A weekly journal of advocating justice, equality and the preservation of American indenpenndence. Vol. 1, no. 1. (Chicago), Aug 16, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Purdie, Bob Ireland Unfree Permantente Revolution, German, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Van Der Straeten, Serge and Phillippe Danfouy, The Counter Revolution in Ireland, 1974 (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Series V. Nonprint, 1980-1995
  This series consists of flags, sashes, bumper stickers, and other objects demonstrating support for various 19th and 20th century Irish Republican and Irish American support groups. Also included is Prendiville's button collection, an assortment of political buttons from Irish organizations in Ireland and the United States, including Irish Republican Clubs, Irish Northern Aid, Citizens for Irish Justice, and the National Association for Irish Freedom. Complementing the buttons are detailed notes on the objects, created and supplied by Prendville.
  - Button Collection, 1980s-1990s; cuid14996 (Box 6)
  - Bumper stickers and penants, circa 1980s, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Paperweight: James Connolly (sold by Anne Devlin IRC; from Gardiner Place, Dublin (Sinn Fein), undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Silk handerchief/scarf "Remember '98" with images of: Robert Emmet, Wolfe Tone, Henry Joy McCracken, Lord Ed. Fitzgerald, undated; cuid14997 (Box 5, Folder 4)